Guide to the Frederick Samuel Dellenbaugh Collection of Photographs and Drawings of the Colorado River Region
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Frederick Samuel Dellenbaugh collection of photographs and drawings of the Colorado River region.
1870-1934
WA PHOTOS 271
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.48
(7 boxes)
The collection contains approximately 900 photographic prints, relief halftones, postcards, negatives, tintypes, and pen-and-ink drawings depicting the Colorado River region and other areas of the West. The early photographs are by E. O. Beaman, James Fennemore, John K. Hillers, photographers on the 1871 Powell expedition. The collection includes relief halftone prints of their photographs, evidently created for inclusion in Dellenbaugh's books on the Colorado River and the West. In addition, there are photographs by Dellenbaugh and other amateur photographers who traveled to the West, as well as by professionals William Henry Jackson and the Kolb Brothers. Subjects include the Grand, Glen, and Havasu Canyons, the Colorado and Green Rivers, Zion National Park, miscellaneous photographs of Arizona, California Colorado, and Utah, and portraits of expedition members and Native Americans. There are 24 drawings by Dellenbaugh which were used as illustrations in Romance of the Colorado and Breaking the West.
Dellenbaugh, Frederick Samuel, 1853-1935
Beaman, E. O. (Elias Olcott), 1837-1876
Fennemore, James, 1849-1941
Hillers, John K., 1843-1925
Klemm, Robert C.
Powell, John Wesley, 1834-1902
Scharff, Seward
Kolb Bros
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired from Edward Eberstadt & Sons.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Box 8 (cold storage): Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
FREDERICK SAMUEL DELLENBAUGH (1853-1935)
Frederick Samuel Dellenbaugh, artist, topographer, explorer and author, was born September 13, 1853 in McConnelsville, Ohio. After graduating from high school in Buffalo, New York, Dellenbaugh's interest in painting and boating led his uncle Almon Harris Thompson to introduce him to John Wesley Powell. Thompson was Powell's brother-in-law and served as second-in-command and chief topographer of Powell's second expedition down the Colorado River in 1871-1873. Powell appointed the seventeen year old Dellenbaugh expedition artist and assistant topographer.
The expedition embarked at Green River, Wyoming, and passed the winter of 1871-72 at Kanab, Utah. In the early spring and summer of 1872, Dellenbaugh and Thompson explored north of Kanab through Potato Valley and discovered the Escalante River, the last major river discovered in the contiguous United States. They continued on to the Aquarius Plateau and the Henry Mountains. In August and September 1872, the expedition traveled through the Upper Grand Canyon, but Powell called a halt to the expedition at Kanab Creek, due to the dangerous currents in the Canyon. The group spent the winter of 1872-1873 creating a map of the area they had explored.
Following the expedition, Dellenbaugh traveled in the West, lived with the Hopi Indians for six months, and studied painting in France. He married Harriet Otis in 1885 and settled in New York. There he wrote and lectured about the West, publishing in 1902 The Romance of the Colorado River and in 1908, A Canyon Voyage, which described the second Powell expedition.
In 1899, Dellenbaugh served as expedition artist on E. H. Harriman's expedition to Alaska and Siberia. In 1906, he accompanied Harriman on an expedition to Spitzbergen, Norway. In later years he continued to travel in the West, served as librarian to the National Geographic Society, and founded the Explorer's Club. He died in New York City on January 29, 1935.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains approximately 900 photographic prints, relief halftones, postcards, negatives, tintypes, and pen-and-ink drawings depicting the Colorado River region and other areas of the West, and portraits of Native Americans. The photographs were collected by Frederick Samuel Dellenbaugh and date from 1871-1934. The collection is organized into two series: Photographs and Drawings. Box 7 contains Oversize material. Restricted Fragile Papers contains negatives; photographic prints produced from these negatives have been supplied in Series I, Photographs, as surrogates.
Series I, Photographs, (boxes 1-5) contains early photographs by E. O. Beaman, James Fennemore, and John K. Hillers, photographers on the 1871 Powell expedition. The collection also includes relief halftones of their photographs, which evidently were created to be used as illustrations for Dellenbaugh's books, primarily The Romance of the Colorado River and A Canyon Voyage. In addition, there are photographs by Dellenbaugh and other amateur photographers who traveled in the West, as well as by professionals, including William Henry Jackson and the Kolb Brothers. Locations depicted include Grand Canyon, Glen Canyon, and Havasu Canyon, the Colorado and Green Rivers, Zion National Park, miscellaneous photographs of Arizona, California, Colorado, and Utah. The portraits are of expedition members and Native Americans.
The photographs are organized alphabetically by photographer: under each photographer, they are listed alphabetically by subject. The photographs were primarily identified by caption information. Where captions were not present, identifications were drawn from reference to Dellenbaugh's published works. Unidentified photographs are listed at the end of the series, arranged by subject. Many of these are early albumen prints and may be by Beaman, Fennemore, or Hillers. Copy prints produced from negatives acquired with the collection are interfiled where appropriate.
Series II, Drawings, (box 6) contains 24 drawings by Dellenbaugh which were used as illustrations in The Romance of the Colorado River and Breaking the West.
Oversize, (box 7) contains material from Series I, and is organized in box order.
Arizona -- Pictorial works; Colorado River (Colo.-Mexico) -- Pictorial works; Colorado -- Pictorial works; Glen Canyon National Recreation Area (Utah and Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; Grand Canyon National Park (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; Green River (Wyo.) -- Pictorial works; Havasu Canyon (Ariz.) -- Pictorial works; Utah -- Pictorial works; Zion National Park (Utah) -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints -- West (U.S.); Tintypes (prints); Beaman, E. O. (Elias Olcott), 1837-1876; Dellenbaugh, Frederick Samuel, 1853-1935 -- Portraits; Fennemore, James, 1849-1941; Hillers, John K., 1843-1925; Klemm, Robert C.; Powell, John Wesley, 1834-1902; Scharff, Seward; Kolb Bros
- Photographs, 1871-1934; Series I; 2.1; (5 boxes)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Photographs, is organized alphabetically by photographer, and listed alphabetically by subject. Unidentified photographs are listed at the end of the series, arranged by subject. Many of these unidentified photographs are early photographs and may be by Beaman, Fennemore, or Hillers.
  - ALTER, J. CECIL
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - BABBITT BROTHERS TRADING CO.
    - Arizona, [1928] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - BARNES, WILL C.
    - Arizona, 1933 Jul (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Portraits, 1933 Jul 6 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - BARTKELMESS, C.
    - Grand Canyon (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - BEAMAN, E. O.
    - Colorado, 1871 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 7, folder 171
    - Glen Canyon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Grand Canyon (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Green River, 1871, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 10-11)
    - Kanab Canyon, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Native Americans, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Utah, 1871, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - BELL'S STUDIOS
    - Portraits, n.d.
  - BROWN EXPEDITION
    - Utah, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - C.C. PIERCE & CO.
    - California, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Yosemite, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - CARTER, [----?], DR.
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - CHAPMAN, R. H.
    - Montana, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - CHINCDINST, [----?]
    - Portraits, n.d.
  - COLE, LEON J.
    - Ohio, 1901 Nov 20 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - COLIN, [----]
    - California, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Grand Canyon, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - DAVIS, ARTHUR P.
    - California, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - DELLENBAUGH, FREDERICK SAMUEL
    - Alaska, 1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Arizona (copy print), n.d. (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - California, 1921, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Columbia River, 1899, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Grand Canyon, 1903-34, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 29-32)
      Includes copy prints.
    - Green River, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Havasu Canyon, 1903-07, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 34-35)
    - Kanab Canyon, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 36-37)
    - Michigan (copy prints), 1905 (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Native Americans, 1884, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - New Mexico, 1907, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - New York, 1921 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Portraits, 1886-1903, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Utah, 1903-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 43-45)
    - Virgin River and Valley (copy prints), 1903, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Wyoming, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Yosemite, 1921, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 48-49)
    - Zion, 1903-29, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 50-51)
    - Unidentified, 1903, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 52-53)
  - DENVER, COLORADO CANYON AND PACIFIC RAILWAY SURVEY
    - Colorado River, 1908 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - DETROIT PUBLISHING CO.
    - Grand Canyon, [1910] (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - DUKANE SCIENCE
    - Florida, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - FENNEMORE, JAMES
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Glen Canyon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Utah, 1872, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - FINTAK, [----]
    - Grand Canyon, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - FLORIDA SOUVENIR CO.
    - Florida, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - FLY'S GALLERY
    - Arizona, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - FRASER, GEORGE C.
    - Colorado River, 1930 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - FRASHER'S INC.
    - Grand Canyon, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - FRAZIER, RUSSELL G.
    - Glen Canyon, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Utah, 1933 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - FRED HARVEY
    - Grand Canyon, 1916-34 (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - GILL, DELANCY
    - Portraits, 1902 Jul 1 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - GOLDRING, WINIFRED
    - Grand Canyon, 1929 (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - GOODMAN, CHARLES
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - HILLERS, JOHN K.
    - Arizona, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Grand Canyon (Box 2, Folder 73)
    - Kanab Canyon, n.d. (Box 2, Folder 74)
    - Native Americans, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 75)
    - Portraits, 1872, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - Utah, 1872, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 77)
    - Virgin River and Valley (Box 3, Folder 78)
    - Wayne County, 1875
    - Zion, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 79)
    - Unidentified, ca. 1878 (Box 3, Folder 80)
  - INT. ART & NOV. CO.
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 81)
  - JACKSON, WILLIAM HENRY
    - Colorado, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 82)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 7, folder 175
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - JOHNSON, L. H.
    - Arizona, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 84)
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 85)
    - Portraits, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 86)
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - JONES, RANDALL
    - Grand Canyon, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 88)
    - Portraits, 1929 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - KELLY, CHARLES
    - Glen Canyon, 1932 Aug (Box 3, Folder 90)
    - Green River, 1933 (Box 3, Folder 91)
    - Portraits, 1932 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - KLEMM, ROBERT C.
    - Grand Canyon, 1926 Nov (Box 3, Folder 93)
    - New Mexico, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - KOLB BROS.
    - Grand Canyon, 1912-28, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 95-97)
    - Green River, 1911 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - LEONARD, R. G.
    - Unidentified, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - LIPPINCOTT, J. B.
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - LIPPINCOTT, OLIVER
    - Grand Canyon, 1898 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - MCDONALD, PRESTON
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - MACDOUGAL, D. T.
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - NUSSBAUM, [----?]
    - Utah, 1920 Oct (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - OASTLER, FRANK RICHARD
    - Glen Canyon, 1925 Jul (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - OTIS, T. A., MRS.
    - Grand Canyon, 1931 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - POMROY, H. ARTHUR
    - Arizona, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - PRUDDEN, T. MITCHELL
    - Grand Canyon (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - PUTNAM & VALENTINE
    - Grand Canyon (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - ROSE, MILLIE
    - Arizona, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - RUST, DAVID D.
    - Glen Canyon, 1923 (Box 3, Folder 111)
    - Portraits, [1931] (Box 3, Folder 112)
    - Utah, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 113)
  - SAVAGE, C. R.
    - Native Americans, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 114)
    - Zion, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - SCHARFF, SEWARD
    - Arizona, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 116)
    - Colorado, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 117)
    - Grand Canyon, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 118)
    - Utah, 1924, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 119)
  - SIMPSON, W. H.
    - Grand Canyon (Box 4, Folder 120)
  - STARR, W. I.
    - Grand Canyon
  - STITES, R. T.
    - Wayne County, 1926, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 121)
  - STONE, JULIUS T.
    - Colorado River, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 122)
    - Grand Canyon, 1909 (Box 4, Folder 123)
  - THORNE, GERALD
    - Green River, 1929-30 (Box 4, Folder 124)
      Accompanied by a TLS from Thorne to Dellenbaugh dated 1930 Apr 29
  - U.S. DEPARTMENT OF THE INTERIOR
    - Zion, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 125)
  - WEETER, JOHN C.
    - Idaho, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 126)
  - WITTICK, BEN
    - Arizona, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 127)
  - [YOUNG?, ----]
    - Portraits, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 128)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PHOTOGRAPHERS
    - Arizona, 1903, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 129)
    - Boston and California Company (Box 4, Folder 130)
    - California, 1934 Sep (Box 4, Folder 131)
    - Canada, 1921 (Box 4, Folder 132)
    - Colorado, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 133)
    - Colorado River, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 134)
    - The Fontenelle, Missouri River boat, drawing by B. Vitzthum, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 135)
    - Glen Canyon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 136)
    - Grand Canyon, 1872-1929, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 137-141)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 7, folder 177
    - Green River, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 142)
      Stored also in: Oversize, box 7, folder 178
    - Havasu Canyon, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 143)
    - Idaho, 1899 (Box 4, Folder 144)
    - Ives' boat, by H. B. Mollhausen, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 145)
    - Kanab Canyon, 1903, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 146)
    - Mexico, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 147)
    - Missouri, 1929 (Box 4, Folder 148)
    - Native Americans, n.d. (Box 4, Folder 149)
    - Nevada, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 150)
    - New Mexico, 1907, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 151)
    - Ogden Canyon, 1929 (Box 5, Folder 152)
    - Portraits, 1870-1929, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 153)
    - Utah, 1871-1929, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 154-156)
    - Virgin River and Valley, 1903, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 157-158)
    - Wyoming, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 159)
    - Zion, 1903-29, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 160-162)
    - Unidentified, 1907, n.d. (Box 5, Folder 163-167)
- Drawings, n.d.; Series II; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Drawings for Breaking the Wilderness, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 168)
  - Drawings for Romance of the Colorado River, n.d. (Box 6, Folder 169)
  - "Hidatsa and Dakota Feather-marks, etc." (Box 6, Folder 170)
- Oversize, 1.17; (1 box)
  Oversize contains material from series I, organized in box order.
  - Beaman, E. O. Colorado River (in Series I) (Box 7, Folder 171)
  - Bell's Studios. Portraits (in Series I), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 172)
  - Chincdinst. Portraits (in Series I), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 173)
  - Hillers, John K. Wayne County (in Series I), 1875 (Box 7, Folder 174)
  - Jackson, William Henry. Colorado (in Series I), n.d. (Box 7, Folder 175)
  - Starr, W. I. Grand Canyon (in Series I) (Box 7, Folder 176)
  - Unidentified. Grand Canyon (in Series I) (Box 7, Folder 177)
  - Unidentified. Green River (in Series I), 1871 (Box 7, Folder 178)
  - Unidentified. Portraits (in Series I), 1884, 1907 (Box 7, Folder 179)
- Restricted Fragile Papers, 0.21; (1 box)
  Restricted Fragile Papers contains negatives for which contact prints have been made. The negatives may only be seen with the permission of the appropriate curator. Photographic prints from the negatives have been substituted in appropriate folders.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folders 26, 32, 35, 37 (Box 8 (Cold Storage), Folder 180)
  - Box 2, folders 38, 40, 43, 45-46, 48-51, 53 (Box 8 (Cold Storage), Folder 181)
  - Box 4, folder 132 (Box 8 (Cold Storage), Folder 182)
  - Box 5, folder 156 (Box 8 (Cold Storage), Folder 183)